David Rapaport Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Part I: Speeches, Writings, and Lectures File, 1911-1960 (Box I:47-76)
  - "Some Problems in Psychoanalysis and Psychopathology"
  - "The Psychoanalytic Model," 1951
  - "Psychoanalysis Versus the Conditioned-Response Theory," 1954
  - "The Prerequisites of a Psychoanalytic Psychology," 1956
  - "The Need for Theoretical Orientation in Clinical Psychology"
  - "Some Problems Facing Psychology and Particularly Clinical Psychology," 1954
  - "Organic Psychoses"
  - "Psychoanalytic Theory of Psychoses", (2 folders)
  - Future research material
  - Research interests, Austen Riggs Center, Stockbridge, Mass., circa 1947-1948
  - "Research Strategy and Tactics," 1951
  - "Clinical Research, or How to Achieve Validity Without Losing Meaningfulness," 1956
  - Patient and Staff Organization seminar, Austen Riggs Center, Stockbridge, Mass., 1958
  - Notes
    - Various seminars, 1956-1960
    - Topology talk, 1948 (Box I:75)
  - Miscellaneous notes found in office
  - Freud, Sigmund, activity and passivity, 1911-1937
  - Seminars, Austen Riggs Center, Stockbridge, Mass., 1950-1955
  - "Psychic Structure Development," 1951
  - "Psychoanalytic Theory of Thinking," Montreal, Canada, 1949
  - "Thinking," Yale University, New Haven, Conn., 1951
  - "The Problems Toward a Theory of Thinking," Clark University, Worcester, Mass., 1952
  - "The Theory of Thinking, Psychodynamics, and Test Rationale, Philadelphia, Pa., 1954
  - "On the Theory of Thinking," Clark University, Worcester, Mass., 1954
  - "Research in the Psychology of Thought Processes," Downey, Ill.
  - "Thought Processes in Schizophrenic Reactions," 1952
  - "The Psychology of Thought Processes," 1952
  - "Experimental Studies into the Organization of Thought," 1956
  - "Time Experience"
  - Reports of discussions on the metapsychology of time, 1948
  - "Defense Versus Id Dynamics" (Box I:76)
  - Ego psychology lectures, collected material
  - Freud, Sigmund, his influence
  - "Conditioning and Learning"
  - Metapsychology material from Rapaport and Merton Max Gill
  - Working notes on superego
  - Reviews
  - Notes and excerpts, (6 folders)
  - Notes for paper on operational definition versus clinical method
- Part II: David Rapaport Papers, 1936-1993 (Box II:1-3)
  Correspondence, drafts of writings and lectures, notes on dreams, biographical material, and bibliographies.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Biographical and bibliographic material, circa 1950-1993 (Box II:1)
  - General correspondence
    - Original letters
      - From an unidentified individual, 1953
      - To
        - Friends concerning trip to Hungary, 1960
        - Rapaport, Béla and Helen (parents), 1948
    - Photocopies of outgoing letters, 1945-1960, undated, (2 folders)
    - Miscellany, 1961, undated
  - Notes on dreams
    - 1941
    - 1948
      - Aug.-Sept., (3 folders)
      - Oct. (Box II:2)
    - 1953-1958, undated
  - Patient file, 1942 See Closed
  - Writings and lectures
    - Alvás Aluszekonysag Álmatkanság, 1936, (2 folders)
    - Freud's Influence on American Psychology, 1959
    - Lélektan, 1938
    - Seminars on Elementary Metapsychology, 1957-1959, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box II:3)
- Part II: Elvira Rapaport Strasser Papers, 1941-1997 (Box II:3-5)
  Correspondence and printed matter.
  - General correspondence (Box II:3)
    - Alphabetical file
      - Fonseca, Hanna Rapaport (daughter)
        - From
          - Originals
            - 1941, 1952-1982, (7 folders)
            - 1983-1989, (3 folders) (Box II:4)
          - Typed transcripts
            - 1957-1984, (5 folders)
            - 1985-1989 (Box II:5)
        - To See Containers II:6-7, Fonseca, Hanna Rapaport
    - Chronological file, 1960, 1973, 1986-1997
  - Miscellany, 1980, 1990-1995
  - Subject file
    - Austen Riggs Center, Stockbridge, Mass.
      - Correspondence, 1962-1966, 1984, 1990-1997
      - Printed matter, 1984, 1990-1996
    - Friedman, Lawrence J., proposed Rapaport biography, 1990-1996
    - Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Jerusalem, Israel, 1959-1970, 1990-1994, undated
- Part II: Formerly Closed, 1934-1996 (Box II:6-14)
  Correspondence, legal documents, and drafts of writings.
  Arranged and described according to the series, containers, and folders from which the items were removed.
  - David Rapaport Papers (Box II:6)
    - Correspondence
      - Original letters
        - From
          - Strasser, Elvira Rapaport (wife), 1935-1945, 1952
  - Elvira Rapaport Strasser Papers
    - General correspondence
      - Alphabetical file
        - Brunner, Andrew Michael, 1971-1995, (3 folders)
        - Dietrick, Joyce Minkler, 1964-1996
        - Fabian, Eli, 1963-1993, (2 folders)
        - Fonseca, Dhiren and Kamini, 1973-1996
        - Fonseca, Hanna Rapaport
          - 1934-1937, 1952, 1964-1972
          - 1973-1989, (2 folders) (Box II:7)
        - Fonseca, Rory, 1963-1964, 1970-1995, (2 folders)
        - Gill, Harriet, 1962-1990
        - Gill, Merton Max, 1962-1992
        - Graf, Enid, 1971-1996
        - Harris, Suzanne, 1962-1974, undated
        - Hewitt, Edwin, 1967-1971
        - Kitschmann, Barbara, 1968-1993
        - Kramer-Lasser, Edna, 1965-1984, undated (Box II:8)
        - Krel, Ibi, 1951, 1961-1963, undated
        - Kudelka, John and Kay, 1965-1984
        - Langer, Bracha, 1964-1977
        - Lányi, Dezsöné (Ili Radó), 1971-1986, undated
        - Levinson, Hank, 1967-1993, undated
        - Márton, Zwi, 1968-1972
        - Maslow, Panni, 1964-1990, (2 folders)
        - Moore, Eleanor and Neal, 1965-1994
        - Phillips, Juliet Rapaport (daughter)
          - From
            - 1960-1969
            - 1970-1992, (6 folders) (Box II:9)
            - 1993-1996 (Box II:10)
          - To, 1952-1953, 1964-1996, (2 folders)
        - Phillips family, 1963-1989, undated
        - Rapaport, David, 1935-1953
        - Roskies, Dodie, Ralph, and family, 1963, 1970-1987
        - Somló, Eva and Pierre, 1962-1985, undated
        - Sulyok, Ernó, 1964-1981
        - Wasserberger, Michel, 1971-1978
        - Zippin, Frances, 1971-1993, undated
      - Chronological file (Box II:11)
        - Incoming letters
          - 1948-1949, 1958-1983, (5 folders)
          - 1984-1994, undated (Box II:12)
        - Outgoing letters, 1964-1994, (5 folders)
    - Subject file
      - Legal cases
        - Strasser v. Basic Books, 1960-1990, (3 folders)
        - Strasser v. Commissioner of Internal Revenue, 1963-1988, undated, (4 folders) (Box II:13)
    - Writings
      - Hungarian song translations, 1986, 1996, undated
      - Memoirs, 1991-1994, (2 folders)
      - Miscellaneous, 1983-1995
      - Poetry, 1982-1996 (Box II:14)
- Part II: Closed, 1942 (Box II:X 15)
  Patient file.
  Arranged and described according to the series, container, and folder from which the item was removed.
  - David Rapaport Papers (Box II:X 15)
    - Patient file, 1942 (Container II:2)